<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Aditya</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Aditya</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Aditya © 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 17:20:32 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Incentive Flipping</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/05/01/incentive-flipping/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 17:20:32 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/05/01/incentive-flipping/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of my favorite pet peeves is the incentive misalignment of doctors. In a very simplified format, the problem is doctors make more money the sicker you are and thus they have a perverse incentive that competes against them making you get better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This incentive misalignment problem is also present in fields like consulting where the consultants get paid more if there are more problems in the company that they can solve, but the doctor problem is the example that I use most of the time to introduce the idea since it&amp;rsquo;s very starkly visible in that case and most people would have experienced it at some point &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Decentralization Is a Quality</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/02/19/decentralization-is-a-quality/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 00:19:26 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/02/19/decentralization-is-a-quality/</guid><description>&lt;p>Decentralization and distributed system are relatively old terms in computing that are getting more widely used outside of these circles. Most of this adoption can be attributed to one phenomenon, crypto.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Decentralization is as the name suggests refers to systems without a center. This is in contrast to a centralized system where the center is the source of truth, control, dispute resolution, etc. all of which still need to be solved in a decentralized system but are done so without a center. Distributed on the other hand refers to systems that are spread out over multiple things (nodes, processors, etc.). For this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing on decentralized systems, but often decentralized systems rely on distributed state&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, so I&amp;rsquo;ll be referring to systems that arise due to both of these qualities interworking.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Qualities and Business Models</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/02/08/qualities-and-business-models/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 13:20:18 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/02/08/qualities-and-business-models/</guid><description>&lt;p>At an abstract level, people generally use tools and technologies primarily for three reasons, to make money, to save money, or to save time. All technologies have to provide at least one (ideally all three) of these benefits to their users for the overhead of using them. This is true for all tools and technologies from the primitive tools used to create fire to modern computers used to solve all kinds of problems.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Connecting People</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/01/24/connecting-people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 16:58:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/2022/01/24/connecting-people/</guid><description>&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A buddy of mine&amp;rdquo; has been building a dating app, so I’ve been thinking a lot about services which connect people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In an abstract sense a lot of the companies today are services which connect people in some context. For example&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Tinder / Dating Apps : Connecting people in the context of dating&lt;/li>
&lt;li>LinkedIn / Other Job Service Portals : Connecting people in the context of job finding&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Facebook / Twitter / Social Media : Connecting people in a generalized context [Often manifested as information sharing, community organizing etc.]&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There are also services such as&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>