<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Newsletter on Aditya</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/newsletter/</link><description>Recent content in Newsletter on Aditya</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright Aditya © 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 16:52:59 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/newsletter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OpenAI, Microsoft, Apple VR &amp; Other Things</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/newsletter/2023-02/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 16:52:59 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/newsletter/2023-02/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hey there!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Welcome to the second edition of the newsletter, which contains news that caught my eye (mostly those that broke in the last week, but no hard constraints) along with an assortment of links and my brief notes to anything that I have found interesting.&lt;br>
Let&amp;rsquo;s get to it!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="news">News&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>OpenAI and ChatGPT
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>More news emerged regarding the &lt;a href="https://fortune.com/2023/01/11/structure-openai-investment-microsoft/">deal structure of OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s funding from Microsoft and other VCs&lt;/a>. According to the article Microsoft has already invested $3 billion in OpenAI and it plans to invest $10 billion further.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/openai-begins-piloting-chatgpt-professional-a-premium-version-of-its-viral-chatbot/">OpenAI plans to monetize ChatGPT with ChatGPT Professional&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are early &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2023/01/chatgpt-written-malware.html">reports of ChatGPT generated or at least assisted malware&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are new &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2023-01-08/when-will-apple-launch-the-reality-pro-mixed-reality-headset-apple-2023-devices-lcnfzkc7">reports of Apple&amp;rsquo;s plan to launch a mixed-reality headset&lt;/a>. &lt;a href="https://fortune.com/2023/01/09/apple-vr-headset-mixed-use-debut-wwdc-2023/">Fortune&lt;/a> builds on top of this article and sets Meta&amp;rsquo;s VR ambition in context with Apple&amp;rsquo;s planned release of &amp;ldquo;Reality Pro&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The headlining &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/the-app-economy-slowed-for-the-first-time-in-2022-with-consumer-spend-down-2-to-167-billion/">consumer spending on mobile apps declined by 2% in 2022 YoY&lt;/a> statistic obscures much more interesting trends captured in the article and the underlying &lt;a href="https://www.data.ai/en/go/state-of-mobile-2023/">State of Mobile&lt;/a> report by data.ai.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitter
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Twitter is said to be considering &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/01/11/technology/twitter-user-names-elon-musk.html">selling defunct usernames&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/13/23553161/third-party-twitter-clients-apps-outage-twitterific-tweetbot">Twitter also broke a bunch of very popular third-party clients&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/theinformation/status/1614398769570668547">The Information reported&lt;/a> that this was deliberate decisions.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90834226/jpmorgan-chase-frank-closed-student-aid-startup-fake-users">JP Morgan is suing Charlie Javice from Frank&lt;/a> among others over allegations of being misled on the number of users of the product. Charlie Javice was yet another person on the Forbes 30 under 30 list which also previously listed &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/30-under-30/2021/finance/">Sam Bankman-Fried&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There were continued reports of layoffs, by multiple companies including &lt;a href="https://www.flexport.com/blog/flexport-co-ceos-note-to-employees/">Flexport&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://verily.com/blog/one-verily-forward/">Verily from Alphabet&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.coinbase.com/blog/a-message-from-ceo-and-co-founder-brian-armstrong-to-coinbase-employees">Coinbase&lt;/a> and not to be outdone by tech companies even &lt;a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90832503/goldman-sachs-layoffs-loom-wall-street-tech-job-cuts">Goldman Sachs&lt;/a>. &lt;a href="https://news.crunchbase.com/layoffs/january-is-already-breaking-layoff-records">Crunchbase&lt;/a> reports Jan of 2023 as the second largest layoff month (in terms of employees) since they started tracking job cuts since Jan 2022.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>On a related note &lt;a href="https://zapier.com/blog/secondments-at-zapier/">Zapier&lt;/a> has a relatively different way of handling the market environment, where instead of laying people off from a team that was overstaffed, they up/cross-skilled them and staffed them to a different team which needed to hire. And there is already a new term for this &amp;ldquo;quiet hiring&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>After the Southwest issue (mentioned in the last issue), there was another &lt;a href="https://edition.cnn.com/travel/article/faa-ground-stop-causes/index.html">technical issue this time at FAA which disrupted flights across the US&lt;/a>. This time it looks like an issue that escalated out of control when officials tried to reboot a system which eventually led to downtime on the central database for all NOTAMs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And to finally end, a story to invoke Deja Vu, &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-01-09/ship-grounded-in-egypt-s-suez-canal-says-leth-agencies">Bloomberg&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/01/09/bulk-carrier-ship-glory-grounded-in-suez-canal-says-shipping-agency.html">CNBC&lt;/a> reported for a brief period there was another ship which suffered a failure in the Suez Canal causing minor inconveniences again on one of the world&amp;rsquo;s busiest naval chokepoint.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="movies-and-documentaries">Movies and Documentaries&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WBMcoJWo92Y">China&amp;rsquo;s Unmarried &amp;lsquo;Leftover&amp;rsquo; Women&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A VICE documentary covering one of the surprising side effects of China&amp;rsquo;s one-child policy. China has a relatively high human-sex ratio i.e, more males than females. Somewhat surprisingly this has also increased pressure on women to get married due to a lot of reasons including societal pressure and media. This &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4mCVS20gj_8">New York Times Op-Doc&lt;/a> focuses on a single woman and is a much more intimate look into the effects on the individuals.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="podcasts">Podcasts&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://a16z.simplecast.com/episodes/creators-creativity-and-technology-with-bob-iger-L98rXqw2">Creators, Creativity, and Technology with Bob Iger&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Bob Iger&amp;rsquo;s conversation with Chris Dixon and Sonal Chokshi. Mostly about his first term as Disney&amp;rsquo;s CEO.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cyberbunker | &lt;a href="https://malicious.life/episode/episode-201/">Part 1&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://malicious.life/episode/episode-202/">Part 2&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Covering the story of Cyberbunker a bulletproof hosting service provider that used to host The Pirate Bay and one of WikiLeaks mirrors among other sites from its inception to its end.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="videos">Videos&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZYj4NkeGPdM">HACKENBUSH: a window to a new world of math&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A video that starts out with a fun game, brings in some basic math ideas to simplify and understand the game, introduces notation to keep up, and suddenly explodes to a lot of notations until you get lost and it finally closes off with a book recommendation. It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful video accompanied by pleasant music where at times I felt like maybe the abstractions being built are a bit too stretched and janky, maybe because I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand the scope of its usage. Nonetheless, the video tries to show how accommodating the notations and abstractions built are to various other games.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6reLWfFNer0">How to Build a Startup Without Funding by Pieter Levels&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pieter Levels who has built multiple companies (notably nomadlist, remoteok) talks about his process of building and launching stuff.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AUFvA9Dr0bA">History of the entire Church, I guess&amp;hellip;&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Before watching this I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know Christianity had so many denominations. With my very limited understanding of religions, it looks like, unlike Hinduism where the groups get created primarily out of the abundance of gods and thus different worshippers of different gods (I&amp;rsquo;m simplifying obviously, there are other different reasons groups get created), in Christianity where there is primarily one sole entity the denominations seem to get created on the different interpretations of the saying of god or who/what god is. Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s not as simple as that, as the video gets to there are denominations that have formed during different times in history to align the concept and make it more amiable to the time.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xiKg3zifRXQ">Scientists whose lives were total dumpster fires&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Among others, it covers the life story of Guillaume Le Gentil, an astronomer who wanted to observe the transit of Venus to measure the distance from the Earth to the Sun but to put it lightly the circumstances didn&amp;rsquo;t allow for it.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="links">Links&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>A very interesting &lt;a href="https://www.netinterest.co/p/insuring-the-unknown-ee1">article on the reinsurance industry&lt;/a>. It provides an introduction to what it does and more interestingly taking a specific example of Berkshire Hathaway how it does. One of the highlights for me was how not over-specifying risk is an important thing when dealing with unknowns. Although Ajit Jain (Berkshire&amp;rsquo;s key underwriter) talks about how they &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/ecDIns2OqqM?t=72">start out with as much science as possible&lt;/a>, post a certain point over-specifying an unknown is an act in self-delusion. The general tendency when over-specifying is in some sense similar to removing the slack out of a system, the more granular you go the more you think you&amp;rsquo;ve covered the space and the more confidence you get in removing broad-level estimates.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Microsoft, ChatGPT, CES &amp; Other Things</title><link>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/newsletter/2023-01/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 02:51:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://adityarsuryavamshi.github.io/newsletter/2023-01/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hey there!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Welcome to the first edition of the newsletter, which contains news that caught my eye (mostly those that broke in the last week, but no hard constraints) along with an assortment of links and my brief notes to anything that I have found interesting.&lt;br>
Let&amp;rsquo;s get to it!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="news">News&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The biggest news that caught my eye this week was &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/4/23538552/microsoft-bing-chatgpt-search-google-competition">Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s plan to integrate Bing with ChatGPT&lt;/a>. Google seems to be already aware of the risks of ChatGPT as indicated by their &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/12/21/technology/ai-chatgpt-google-search.html">&amp;ldquo;code red&amp;rdquo; declaration&lt;/a>.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>ChatGPT has already had a lot of adoption from new products built on top of it to existing companies like &lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/product/ai">Notion&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/integrations/apps/ai-assistant">Todoist&lt;/a> and even &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/wongmjane/status/1610235492909580290">iTerm&lt;/a>. Apart from integrating with a generalized search, it would be these contextual just-in-time prompting where I think this would be more used. Just like most of the google searches of a programmer are for code snippets and documentation, I would assume most searches by most people are bounded in their domains, and integrating ChatGPT or something like that in the relevant and predominant tool of that industry would be most beneficial.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Integration of this with organizational chat tools like Slack, and Mattermost is something I still haven&amp;rsquo;t seen, but done well (which is definitely within the realm of possibility) this solves one of the biggest problems in large organizations, the problem of &amp;ldquo;knowledge discovery&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In other news, I also got to know that Bing already has a &lt;a href="https://www.bing.com/create">image create feature&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In more AI-related news &lt;a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/chatgpt-banned-in-new-york-city-public-schools-over-concerns-about-cheating-learning-development-11673024059">ChatGPT was banned in New York City Public Schools&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/y3p9yg/artist-banned-from-art-reddit">Reddit&amp;rsquo;s /r/Art banned an artist&lt;/a> because the art looked like it was generated with AI. These are the type of news articles that 100 years from now people would look back to, similar to how we look back to news articles condemning the advent of every new technology.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This is not an excuse to discount the critics, they do serve an important purpose in moderating the eventual consensus that gets formed on usage and putting a cap on the hysteria we see during the adoption cycle. The pushback in a lot of cases against the newer wave of AI seems more like a reaction to the lack of time to form a consensus on the longer-term impact of these technologies and where they would be best leveraged rather than the historic Luddite kind of reaction.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CES was this week. Just a couple of years ago my youtube feed during CES was filled with videos from tech YouTubers making dozen of videos covering CES, but this year it&amp;rsquo;s been relatively quiet. Nonetheless, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9kvMAx4-Fm0">Engadget&lt;/a> faithfully covered and summarized the event with their daily recaps.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The most interesting thing to me that I hope gets widely adopted are integrated projector in cars (Regardless of large-scale utility it&amp;rsquo;s just such a fun idea), and the ability to plug in a headphone jack to your wireless earbud case which then pushes that audio to your wireless earbuds.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>CES being primarily a hardware-focused show likely has a lag in terms of embedded technology adoption, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t a lot of headlining ChatGPT level AI integration, but for some reason, there was a Samsung announcement that used blockchain for some element of home automation.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>More details on the &lt;a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/southwest-airlines-melting-down-flights-cancelled-11672257523">Southwest meltdown came this week&lt;/a>. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t actively follow this story when it came out the surrounding discussion makes it seem more like an actual technology/management problem than I initially thought. The first pass of the blame seems to be on Skysolver (what looks like a constraint solver) software being used by Southwest. It&amp;rsquo;s still very unclear what and how exactly it failed. But like all software-related disruptions, the operators seem to have known of the fragility of the system.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Some of the quotes from the article&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>